William Mills Ivins
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Professional and Personal Papers, 1908-1961, Series 1:; (Boxes 1-6; 6 linear ft.)
  - Correspondence, A-Z, 1908-1961, 1.1:
    - Troxell, Janet, 1954-1959 (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
    - Correspondence, U (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - University of Chicago, 1932-1945 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      (includes U.C. Press)
    - Correspondence, V (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
    - Vasari Society, 1922-1933 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, W (Box 5, Folder 21-27)
      (includes: Watrous, Harry W., 1925; Watson, Forbes, 1926)
    - Wallace, Ed, 1954-1958 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Warburg, Felix M., 1919-1935 (Box 5, Folder 29)
      (about acquisitions for FMW collection)
    - Webster, Herman A., and Mounette, 1910-1959 (Box 5, Folder 30-31)
      (about travels; prints for sale in Europe; WMI's writings; exhibitions of HAW work in U.S.; German occupation of France)
    - Weil, Ernst, 1932-1955 (Box 5, Folder 32)
      (about WMI book purchases; see also: Tauber & Weil)
    - Wetmore, Edith, 1928-1956 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Weyhe, E., 1948-1959 (Box 5, Folder 34)
      (about WMI book purchases)
    - Wilkinson, Charles, 1946-1961 (Box 5, Folder 35)
      (about MMA staff; travels; news of mutual friends)
    - Wind, Edgar, 1945-1952 (Box 5, Folder 36)
      (about Vesalius; translations; Greek art; aesthetics; his own writings and those of WMI; news of mutual friends)
    - Winlock, Herbert Eustis, 1931-1948 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      (about MMA staff; MMA Egyptian expedition; acquisitions; MMA administration)
    - Winter, Carl, 1939-1943 (Box 5, Folder 38)
      (about Elizabethan miniatures; World War II; book about Nicholas Hilliard; news of mutual friends)
    - Winternitz, Emanuel, 1945-1961 (Box 5, Folder 39)
      (about MMA staff; MMA Musical Instrument Collection; news of mutual friends)
    - Woodbury, Conn. property, 1941-1956 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Woodhouse, Betty Burroughs, 1935-1959 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence, Y (Box 5, Folder 42)
      (includes Young, Art, undated)
    - Yale University, 1942-1958 (Box 5, Folder 43)
      (includes Art GalleryConvocation, 1946; Elizabethan Club; Library; Y.U. Press; Yale Review)
    - Z (Box 5, Folder 44)
      (includes Zigrosser, Carl, 1932-1959)
    - Correspondence, unknown and illegible (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, Correspondence and Office Files, 1919-1947, 1.2:
    The file on European travels contains letters of introduction to curators and collectors, miscellaneous notes, and expense records for museum business. Files on gifts and loans refer to those from WMI's personal collection to the museum. Metropolitan Museum Studies files include records of the Editorial board meetings, 1927-1936; circulation records, 1933; general records, 1931; Vol 4 and 5, 1933-1935; correspondence with and about contributors, including Burroughs, Alan, Cooke, Walter W.S., Cumont, Diamond, W., Dinsmore, William B., Frick, Colin G., Jacobsthal, Lewis, W.S., Morgan, John Hill, Panofsky, Erwin, Planiscig, L., Richter, Gisela A.M., Tietze, Hans, Updike, D.B., and Wehle, H; and rejected articles. Printed matter does not include exhibition catalogs from the museum.
    - Addresses (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    - Calendar, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Employees' Association, 1937-1947 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - European Travels, 1919, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Gifts, 1922-1946 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Loans, 1923-1936 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous letters, notes, etc., 1923-1935 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Pension (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Printed matter issued by Metropolitan Museum (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Print Department (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Publications, notes about (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Restaurant bills (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Durer collection of Junius Spencer Morgan, circa 1919 (Box 6, Folder 15-17)
    - Metropolitan Museum Studies (Box 6, Folder 18-38)
    - Clippings (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - History of Metropolitan Museum of Art by Winifred E. Howe, 1905-1941 (Box 6, Folder 40)
      (galley sheets annotated by WMI)
  - Correspondence with publishers, 1932-1954, 1.3:
    This subseries relates to major publications and is filed by title in chronological order. Additional correspondence regarding Ivins' publications is included in the alphabetical sequence, usually filed under the name of editor, rather than publisher or periodical.
    - On the Rationalization of Sight, Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1948 (Box 7 (hol), Folder 1)
    - Three Vesalian Essays, University of Chicago and New York Academy of Medicine, 1932-1951 (Box 7 (hol), Folder 2-3)
    - Art & Geometry, Harvard University Press and Routledge & Kegan Paul, Ltd., 1945-1951 (Box 7 (hol), Folder 4-5)
    - Prints and Visual Communication, Harvard University Press and Routledge & Kegan Paul, Ltd., 1950-1958 (Box 7 (hol), Folder 6-7)
    - What Makes a Masterpiece?, Harry N. Abrams, Inc., 1953-1945 (Box 7 (hol), Folder 8)
- Writings, 1896-1964, undated, Series 2:; (Boxes 8-14; 7 linear ft.)
  The series is organized into two subseries:
  2.1: Notes, Drafts, and Manuscripts, circa 1913-1956, undated
  2.2: Publications, 1896-1964
  - Notes, Drafts, and Manuscripts, circa 1913-1961, 2.1:
    This subseries consists of notes, drafts, manuscripts, and corrected galley sheets for books, articles, reviews, lectures, etc., by William M. Ivins, Jr., both published and unpublished. Some are in notebooks spanning several years and covering a range of topics, in no apparent order within the volumes. Also included are autobiographical notes, c. 1925-1950's, and leaves from diaries dated 1919 and 1943-1945. Many are untitled and undated.
    As far as possible, the records are arranged in rough chronological order.
    - Notes, Drafts, and Manuscripts, circa 1913-1935 (Box 8, Folder 1-28)
      (includes five notebooks)
    - Notes, Drafts, and Manuscripts, 1936-1943 (Box 9, Folder 1-26)
      (includes Morgan Library lectures, "Aspects of Renaissance Book Illustration"; On the Rationalization of Sight; and How Prints Look)
    - Notes, Drafts, and Manuscripts, 1945-1953 (Box 10, Folder 1-25)
      (includes: University of Chicago lectures, "Mathematics and the Imagination"; Art and Geometry; " Fallacies About Art"; "What About the Fabrica of Vesalius" for Three Vesalian Essays)
    - Notes, Drafts, and Manuscripts, 1953-1956 (Box 11, Folder 1-25)
      (includes Lowell Lectures, Prints and Visual Communication; What Makes a Masterpiece?; Prints: Technique and Expression; and autobiographical notes, circa 1925-1950)
    - Notes, Drafts, and Manuscripts, undated (Box 12, Folder 1-32)
      (includes seven notebooks on geometry, perspective, book illustration, and early etching; articles for Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin, c. 1917-c.1925)
  - Publications, 1896-1954, 2.2:
    This subseries contains an incomplete set of publications by Ivins including books, articles, lectures, exhibition catalogs, and reviews. Many are marked copies, corrected or otherwise annotated by the author. When available, reviews of books and exhibitions are filed with the corresponding volume. The first folder in the subseries contains Ivins' first published work, consisting of letters written to his mother while in South America.
    The publications are arranged in chronological order by date of publication, with later editions and reprints filed by date of first publication.
    - "A Trip Worth Describing, Letters from a Lad While Travelling," Monmouth Democrat [Freehold, N.J.], Dec. 3, 1896 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - "Catalogue of an Exhibition of Prints by Albrecht Durer, With an Introduction by William M. Ivins, Jr.," Frederick Keppel & Co., Nov. 5-31, 1917 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Wood Engravings by Rudolph Ruzicka, Newark Public Library, Marcj 5-31, 1917 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Exhibition of Painter Etchings and Engravings of the XIX Century, Consisting Mainly of Loans From Private Collections, Metropolitan Museum of Art, April 1917 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - The Wood Engravings of Rudolph Ruzicka, The Newark Museum Association, 1917 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - A Catalogue of Italian Renaissance Woodcuts, Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1927 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - "Of Museums," The Arts, vol. III, no. 1, Jan. 1923 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - "Daumier - The Man of His Time," The Arts, vol. III, no. 2 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Loan Exhibition of the Italian Renaissance, Metropolitan Museum of Art, May 7-Sept. 9, 1923 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - "A History of Engraving and Etching by Arthur M. Hind," reviewed by Ivins in The Literary Review, July 21, 1935 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - "A Note on Claude Garamond, Punch-Cutter & Type-Founder," in Monotype, vol. 9, no. 6, 1923 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - A Guide to an Exibition of The Arts of the Book, Metropolitan Museum of Art, May 12-Sept. 14, 1924 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - "Goya's Disasters of War," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XIX, no. 9, Sept. 1924 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - "A Gift of Prints," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XX, no. 8 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - "Joseph Pennell," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXI, no. 11, Aug. 1925 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Prints and Books, Informal Papers, 1926 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - "Photography and the `Modern' Point of View, A Speculation in the History of Taste," Metropolitan Museum Studies, vol. I, pt. l [1928?] (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - "A Note Apropos of Two Anniversaries," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXII, no. 1, Jan. 1928 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - "A Collection of English Trading Cards," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXIII, no. 2, Feb. 1928 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - "Beauty in Architecture," The Arts, vol. XIV, no. 3, Sept. 1928 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - "Philbert de l'Orme's Premiere Tome de l'architecture," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXIV, no. 5, May 1929 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - "Notes on Three Durer Woodblocks," Metropolitan Museum Studies, vo. II, pt. 1, Nov. 1929 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - "Kleiner's Residences Memorables," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXIV, no. 12, Dec. 1929 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - "Vasari's Lives," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1930 (Box 13, Folder 24)
    - "Notes on Two Woodcuts of the Nuremberg School," Metropolitan Museum Studies, vol. II, pt. 3, May 1930 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - Notes on Prints, Being the Text of Labels Prepared for a Sepcial Exhibition of Prints from the Museum Collection, Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1930 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - "French Eighteenth-Century Engravings," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXVI, no. 2, Feb. 1931 (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - Daumier, March 1931 (Box 13, Folder 28)
    - "An Exhibition of Reproductive Prints," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXVI. no.10, Oct. 1931 (Box 13, Folder 29)
    - "Early Woodcuts," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXVII, no. 2, Feb. 1932 (Box 13, Folder 30)
    - "Address at the Cooper Union, Tuesday, 25th of February 1932" (Box 13, Folder 31)
    - Hugh Thompson - His Art, His Letters, His Humor, and His Charm by M.H. Spielmann and Walter Jerrold, reviewed by Ivins in The Saturday Review of Literature, vol. IX, no. 1, July 23, 1932 (Box 13, Folder 32)
    - "Artistic Aspects of Fifteenth-Century Printing," Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America, vol. XXVI, 1932 (Box 13, Folder 33)
    - "An undescribed Schongauer Trial Proof," Metropolitan Museum Studies, vol. IV, pt. 2, March 1933 (Box 13, Folder 34)
    - "Two Woodcuts of the Virgin," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXVII, no. 4, April 1932 (Box 13, Folder 35)
    - "A Woodblock by Brueghel," Metropolitan Museum Studies, vol. V, pt. 1, June 1934 (Box 13, Folder 36)
    - "On Education in a Museum," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXIX, no. 9, Sept. 1934 (Box 13, Folder 37)
    - Bryson Burroughs, Catalogue of a Memorial Exhibition of his Works, Metropolitan Museum of Art, March 25-May 5, 1935 (Box 13, Folder 38)
    - Francisco Goya, His Paintings, Drawings, and Prints, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Jan. 27-March 8, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 39)
    - "The Woodcuts to Vesalius," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXXI, no. 7, July 1936 (Box 13, Folder 40)
    - "The Lovers by the Master b × g, An Undescribed Early German Engraving," Metropolitan Museum Studies, vol. V, pt. 2, Sept. 1936 (Box 13, Folder 41)
    - "Goya's Giant," Metropolitan Museum Studies, vol V, pt. 2, Sept. 1936 (Box 13, Folder 42)
    - "Italian Renaissance Prints and Illustrated Books," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museeum of Art, vol. XXXII, no. 12, Dec. 1937 (Box 13, Folder 43)
    - "Italian Baroque Prints," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXXIII, no. 7, July 1938 (Box 13, Folder 44)
    - On the Rationalization of Sight: With an Examination of Three Renaissance Texts on Perspective. Metropolitan Museum of Art Papers, No. 8, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 45)
    - "Address given at the Opening of the Exhibition of Metropolitan Museum Printing held in the Pierpont Morgan Library on 24 October 1938," 1939 (Box 13, Folder 46)
    - "The Ketham of 1490," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXXVI, no. 2, Feb., 1939 (Box 13, Folder 47)
    - The Artist and the Fifteenth Century Printer, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 48)
    - "The Art of Rembrandt," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. XXXVII, no. 1, Jan. 1942 (Box 13, Folder 49)
    - The Unseen Rembrandt by Ivins, reviewed by Jakob Rosenberg, College Art Journal, vol. 1, no. 4, May 1942 (Box 13, Folder 50)
    - "Renaissance Books on Architecture," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Dec. 1942 (Box 13, Folder 51)
    - "Free Thought in the Country," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Feb. 1943 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - "A Breugel Exhibition in the Print Galleries," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, March 1943 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - "Ignorance, the End," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Summer 1943 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - "A Note on Girard Desargues," Scripta Mathematica, March 1943 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - "A Propos the Fabrica of Vesalius," Bulletin of the History of Medicine, Dec. 1943 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - How Prints Look, 1943, 1948 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - "The Hebal of `Pseudo-Apuleius'," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, March 1944 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - "Early Florentine Illustrated Books," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Summer 1944 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - "But It's Not a Cimabue!," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Dec. 1944 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - "French XVI Century Prints," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, June 1945 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - "Goya," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, June 1945 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - "In the Beginning was the Word," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Summer 1945 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - "The Art Museum Library," The Museum News, vol. 23, no. 8, Oct. 15, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Preface to an American Philosophy of Art, by A. Philip McMahon, reviewed by Ivins, Gazette des Beaux-Arts, [c. 1945] (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - "Tiresome and Baroque," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Feb. 1946 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - "The Aix Lantern," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, March 1946 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - "The 'Field' of Prints, Objects vs. Meanings," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, May 1946 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - "The Dead Hand," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, June 1946; Buffalo Academy of Fine Arts Albright Gallery Notes, Jan. 1947; PSA [Photographic Society of America] Journal, Nov. 1947 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - "Address by William Mills Ivins, Jr. in the Yale Art Gallery, Friday evening," 18 October 1946 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - "The Dances of Death" Printed in Paris in 1490. A Reproduction made from the copy in the Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress, with an introduction by Ivins, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Art & Geometry: A Study in Space Intuition, 1946, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - "A Few Fallacies About Art," Harper's, Aug. 1947 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - "More Fallacies About Art," Harper's, Sept. 1947 (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - "A Note on Desargues' Theorum," Scripta Mathematica, Sept./Dec. 1947 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - "Some Notes on Fakes," Magazine of Art, May 1948 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - "A Note on Ipseity," The Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism, Sept. 1948 (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - "A Neglected Aspect of Early Print-Making," Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Oct. 1948 (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - Leonardo da Vinci: Paragone. A Comparison of the Arts, by Irma A. Richter, reviewed by Ivins, Times Literary Supplement, June 10, 1949 (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - "Some Disconnected Notes About Drawing," Harper's, Dec. 1949 (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Three Vesalian Essays to Accompany the Icones Anatomicae of 1934, with Samuel W. Lambert and Willy Wiegand, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 30)
    - Symmetry by Herman Weyl, reviewed by Ivins, Magazine of Art, April 1953 (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - Prints and Visual Communication, 1953 (Box 14, Folder 32)
    - What Makes a Masterpiece?, 1953; reprinted in Art Digest, March 15, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 33)
    - Prints: Technique and Expression, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 34)
- Miscellaneous, 1915, undated, Series 3:; (box 15; 1 linear ft.)
  This series consists mainly of printed matter (neither by nor about William M. Ivins, Jr.). Most are presentation copies of articles, and other appear to have been saved by Ivins for research purposes. These cover a wide variety of topics, including: book arts, history of medicine, history of science and technology, calligraphy, history of printmaking, psychology of perception, physiology of vision, philosophy, and the U.S. legal and judicial systems.
  Additional miscellaneous materials include non-printed items relating to Ivins' personal life, such as banking records, receipts and invoices for personal purchases (excluding prints and books), drawings by Ivins, and notes and clippings regarding his legal career.
  Material is arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Miscellaneous printed matter, mainly articles on diverse subjects (Box 15, Folder 1-48)
  - Clippings, advertising circulars, etc., no author (Box 15, Folder 49-50)
  - Receipts and invoices for purchases other than prints and books (Box 15, Folder 51)
  - Banking records (Box 15, Folder 52)
  - Clippings and miscellaneous items regarding Ivins' legal career, including Barnes vs. Roosevelt, 1915 (Box 15, Folder 53-54)
- Ivins Family Papers, 1878-1964, undated, Series 4:; (boxes 16-19; 4 linear ft.)
  The Ivins Family Papers consist mainly of correspondence between relatives and friends of the Ivins, 1878-1964, and also include drawings, clippings, genealogies, and miscellaneous items.
  Correspondence between William M. Ivins, Jr., and his mother, Emma Yard Ivins, is extensive and wide-ranging. Included are letters from boarding school, c. 1890-1897, with childhood memorabilia such as grade reports, homework papers, a silhouette, and printed programs from school concerts and athletic events. His letters written while an undergraduate at Harvard, 1897-1901, and during his European trip of 1901-1902, reflect a growing interest in art. During some periods, mother and son corresponded almost daily. He frequently wrote in detail about progress with work, news of the museum, opinions about art, and activities of friends and colleagues, as well as commenting on daily life at home.
  Florence Wyman Ivins (Mrs. William M. Ivins) also wrote to her mother-in-law regularly, mainly family news which often included details of her husband's professional activities.
  The series is organized into eight subseries by individual:
  4.1: Genealogy, undated
  4.2: William M. Ivins, Jr., 1890-1964
  4.3: Barbara Ivins, 1923-1949, undated
  4.4: Emma Yard Ivins, 1878-1940
  4.5: Florence Wyman Ivins, circa 1911-1948, undated
  4.6: Katharine Ivins, 1890s-1962, undated
  4.7: Margaret Ivins Holmes, 1890s-1954
  4.8: Sarah Mills Ivins, 1890s-1910
  4.9: William M. Ivins, Sr., 1891-1924
  Letters addressed to each particular person for whom a subseries exists are arranged alphabetically by sender and filed in chronological order within each name. Related clippings, estate papers, and miscellaneous items are filed with the papers of the person to whom they pertain. There are a few exceptions in this filing system: in cases where there is but one letter addressed to an individual, the item is filed with the papers of the sender, and the authorship clearly indicated in the description.
  - Genealogy, undated, 4.1:
    - Genealogy, notes on family history, and clippings about Ivins/Mills/Perrine families, and Ivins/Yard/Swift families, undated (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - William M. Ivins, Jr., 1890-1964, 4.2:
    Letters from relatives in box 16 include those from Barbara Ivins [daughter], 1922-1961; Emma Yard Ivins [mother], 1892-1939; Florence Wyman Ivins [wife], 1908-1941; and James Sterling Yard Ivins [brother], 1897-1959. Letters from relatives in box 17 include those from (Katharine Ivins [sister], 1909-1961; Margaret Ivins Holmes [sister], 1890's-1954; Sarah Ivins [neice or cousin], 1947-1958; William M. Ivins, Sr., [father], 1893-1915; Willaim T. Mills [grandfather], 1910; Annie Perrine [cousin], 1929-1931; Loraine Wyman Painter [sister-in-law], 1922; Walter C. Wyman [father-in-law], 1916-1924; and Addie Yard [grandmother], 1898.
    Records concerning the estate of Ivins' estate include obituary, memorials and tributes; letters of condolence, A-Z (addressed to Barbara); and Ivins Collection of Prints and Illustrated Books, sales records and auction catalogs, 1962-1964.
    - Letters from relatives, 1892-1961 (Box 16, Folder 3-38)
    - Letters from relatives, 1890-1961 (Box 17, Folder 1-27)
    - Estate of William M. Ivins, Jr., 1961-1964 (Box 17, Folder 28-34)
  - Barbara Ivins 1923-1949, undated, 4.3:
    Barbara Ivins (1913-), daughter of William M. Ivins, Jr., and Florence Wyman Ivins, was the donor of the William M. Ivins, Jr. Papers. She is sometimes addressed as Barbi, Bubbles, Bubsey. Letters found here include those from Florence Wyman Ivins [mother], 1944; Katharine Ivins [aunt], undated; and William M. Ivins, Jr., [father], 1932-1939.
    - Letters from relatives and artwork, 1923-1949, undated (Box 18, Folder 1-4)
  - Emma Yard Ivins, 1878-1940, 4.4:
    Emma Yard Ivins (1857-1940) was the mother of William M. Ivins, Jr. She was an amateur photographer whose work was exhibited at the turn of the century. She was active in the woman's suffrage movement from circa 1900 to 1915. She was sometimes addressed as Nem or Bammie.
    Material relating to the woman's suffrage movement includes letters from Susan B. Anthony, 1900-1906, with a photographic portrait and a printed silhouette. Also included are letters from Ida Husted Harper, 1909 and Anna H. Shaw, 1906-1915. In addition, there is miscellaneous printed matter, 1900-1906, and undated impressions of the suffrage movement in England by an author unknown.
    Miscellaneous records include Christmas lists, 1900-1929; constitution and by-laws of the Wednesday Afternoon Club, 1917-1918, with lists of officers and programs since its establishment in 1888; a certificate from the Woodrow Wilson Foundation, 1922; and clippings about Emma Yard Ivins, 1921.